{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This ruler defeated the Shardana pirates and captured the vassal state of Amurru and the port of Sumur before his campaign against Muwatalli II. This man commissioned his mortuary temple in Thebes and a pair of temples that were relocated in 1968 to accommodate the Aswan High Dam. This husband of Nefertari won the battle of Kadesh against the Hittites, the opponent of his father, Seti I. For 10 points, name this long-ruling New Kingdom Egyptian pharaoh who built Abu Simbel.",
      "answer": "Ramesses the Great"
    },
    {
      "question": "A tribe in this region described as “curly haired” were known as the Silures. Tacitus published a long history of a governor of this region who won the Battle of Mons Graupius. That man, Agricola, fought tribes in this region’s area of Caledonia. A structure built in this region was possibly meant to keep out the Picts and has ”broad and “narrow” portions. For 10 points, name this province, the location of Hadrian’s Wall.",
      "answer": "Roman Britain"
    },
    {
      "question": "After a series of competitions in this sport, two sides engaged in mutual popular boycott after controversy over the Adelaide leak and the bodyline tactic. That tactic neutralized the prowess of one of the greatest athletes to play this sport, Don Bradman, and was part of The Ashes series between England and Australia. This sport has Twenty20, One Day International, and Test varieties. For 10 points, name this sport popular in the British Commonwealth that uses a flat bat and wickets.",
      "answer": "cricket"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the Tummal inscription, this character and his son rebuild a sanctuary to the goddess Ninlil. In another appearance, he hears counsel about the fool being given chaff and about a three-ply rope not being easily broken. This character meets Siduri after mourning a friend for seven days and travels to see the flood survivor Utnapishtim. He defeats Humbaba in a cedar forest with the help of his companion, a former wild-man named Enkidu. For 10 points, name this king of Uruk, the hero of a namesake epic.",
      "answer": "Gilgamesh"
    },
    {
      "question": "This Nobel Prize winning-scientist assisted Germany’s production of chlorine gas and oversaw its use at Second Ypres. This Jewish scientist’s lab ironically developed the predecessor to Zyklon B. This is the alphabetically-latter of the two namesakes of a process utilizing Hess’ Law to calculate lattice energies. While working for BASF, Carl Bosch refined a process named for this man. For 10 points, name this developer of the industrial process of ammonia production.",
      "answer": "Fritz Haber"
    },
    {
      "question": "Its not Italy, but revanchists in this nation supported a cross-border raid called the Pork mutiny, and this nation’s army would commonly surround troops in pockets called motti. One invasion of this nation attempted to split it in half by moving through Raate Road. A sniper known as the White Death fought in one of this nation’s wars, which began after troops attacked the Mannerheim Line. For 10 points, name this nation that resisted a Soviet invasion in the Winter and Continuation Wars.",
      "answer": "Republic of Finland"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization implemented a free breakfast for children program along with community health clinics in attempts to expand outside of Oakland. The FBI infiltrated this group through the COINTELPRO program, and this group used open carry laws to counter police brutality. This group also resisted the draft by ambushing police. For 10 points, name this Maoist radical- left organization founded by Huey Newton and Bobby Seale.",
      "answer": "Black Panther Party for Self-Defense"
    },
    {
      "question": "This rebellion ended when Captain Thomas Grantham tricked its last group of fighters into boarding his ship. The namesake of this rebellion denounced its opponent in the “Declaration of the People” and was replaced by John Ingram after he died of dysentery. This revolt’s namesake member of the House of Burgesses briefly controlled most of Virginia. For 10 points, name this 1676 rebellion against Governor William Berkeley that led to the burning of Jamestown.",
      "answer": "Bacon’s Rebellion"
    },
    {
      "question": "This movement led to the founding of the American Tract Society and involved meetings at Gasper River and Cane Ridge. Influential figures in this movement included Barton Stone and Lyman Beecher. Charles Finney described regions of New York influenced by this movement as “burned-over districts.” For 10 points, identify this period of religious revival which ultimately gave rise to the emergence of Baptism and Methodism, a movement lasting from the early to mid-nineteenth century.",
      "answer": "Second Great Awakening"
    },
    {
      "question": "The oldest German one of these structures was reconstructed from the original stones in 1961. Many ancient forms of these buildings contain zodiac art, such as the one at Beth Alpha near Gilboa. All of these buildings contain a platform called a bimah or tebah for resting a certain text. Since 1970, many American ones have inserted optional mechitza walls to separate the sexes and all have an ark area that faces Jerusalem. For 10 points, name these buildings used for Jewish religious services.",
      "answer": "synagogues"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1965 this institution was the site of LBJ's speech titled \"To Fulfill these Rights.\" Notable figures associated with this institution include sociologist E. Franklin Frazier and philosopher Alain Locke. Named for a Union General that served as Commissioner of the Freedmen's Bureau, its Metro stop is in the Shaw neighborhood. For 10 points, name this historically black university located in Washington, DC.",
        "answer": "Howard University"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other historically black school located in Atlanta employed Howard Zinn as a faculty member and exclusively admits women.",
        "answer": "Spelman College"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One leader of this nation was removed in the People Power Revolution, also known as the Yellow Revolution, following the assassination of Benigno Aquino. General Wainwright surrendered this present day nation to the Japanese while besieged in Corregidor. For 10 points, name this country where American troops experienced the Bataan Death March.",
        "answer": "Republic of the Philippines"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The wife of Philippine dictator Ferdinand Marcos, Imelda Marcos, was known for owning a large number of this article of clothing.",
        "answer": "shoes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The name of one of this man’s works was inspired by a display at the Columbian Exposition in Chicago involving the lowering of the Liberty Bell. Another of his compositions was often used to accompany the two-step and was commissioned by its namesake newspaper, the Washington Post. For 10 points, name this composer of The Stars and Stripes Forever and many other marches.",
        "answer": "John Philip Sousa"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "At the request of Chester Alan Arthur, Sousa composed “Semper Fidelis”, which became the official march of this organization.",
        "answer": "the United States Marine Corps"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader was sent to the Canary islands after the rise of the Popular Front and was a leader of the Foreign Legion during the Rif War. This leader is buried in the Valley of the Fallen, a monument which was built under his rule. This leader joined his Falange party to the Carlists. For 10 points, name this Fascist leader of Spain who won the Spanish Civil War.",
        "answer": "Francisco Franco"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Franco was supported in the Spanish Civil War by this air unit, which bombed Guernica. It was mainly composed of volunteers from Luftwaffe.",
        "answer": "Condor Legion"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Louisiana native Willie Francis sued E. L. Resweber to prevent this action, on the grounds that it had already been unsuccessfully applied to him. Roper v. Simmons placed age restrictions on this action. A set of 1976 cases that held that this action could never be mandatory, but overturned a moratorium on performing it, included Gregg v. Georgia and Furman v. Georgia. For 10 points, identify this sentence often challenged as cruel and unusual punishment, historically carried out by electrocution or lethal injection.",
        "answer": "the death penalty"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This state was the respondent in Atkins, a Supreme Court case prohibiting a capital sentence for mentally handicapped individuals. Pace v. Alabama was overturned in a 1966 case challenging this state’s anti-miscegenation laws.",
        "answer": "Commonwealth of Virginia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Salt water taffy was originally produced and sold in this city. Until his racketeering conviction in 1941, Enoch “Nucky” Johnson ran this city’s political machine. This city's attractions have included Steel Pier, the first Miss America pageants, and a five mile long boardwalk. For 10 points, name this resort city, a gambling hub on the ocean coast of New Jersey.",
        "answer": "Atlantic City"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In October 2012, Atlantic City was buffeted by this hurricane which caused billions of dollars in damage in New Jersey.",
        "answer": "Hurricane Sandy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country, the Dinant Corporation owned by potato chip magnate Miguel Facusse’ has been accused of aiding narcotraffickers. This country was expelled from the OAS after Roberto Micheletti became the head of this nation following the ouster of Manuel Zelaya in a 2009 coup. For 10 points, name this Central American nation, located just north of Nicaragua.",
        "answer": "Republic of Honduras"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Manuel Zelaya was criticized for allying with the leader of what country currently experiencing runaway inflation and rioting and led by the PSUV Party?",
        "answer": "Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "According to a book named after him, this god once spent eight years underground milking cows. This god turned Idunn into a nut to rescue her from her kidnapper Thiazzi. Skadi placed a serpent above this god, whose venom causes him to writhe so violently the earth shakes. This god took the form of a mare to sleep with Svadilfari, a union that produced Sleipnir. For 10 points, identify this trickster god of Norse mythology.",
        "answer": "Loki"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Loki once got kicked out of a party hosted by this god for killing his servant Fimafeng. Like Njord, he was a god of the sea.",
        "answer": "Aegir"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "REFORMATION",
      "prompt": "During the Reformation who or what…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Started the Reformation with his “Ninety-Five Theses?”",
          "answer": "Martin Luther"
        },
        {
          "question": "Emphasized predestination, helping to found Reformed Christianity with his Institutes of the Christian Religion?",
          "answer": "John Calvin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the 1521 meeting that condemned the early stages of the Reformation?",
          "answer": "Diet of Worms"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the meeting that launched the Counter-Reformation?",
          "answer": "Council of Trent"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Latin name for the doctrine which emphasized the singular authority of Biblical text?",
          "answer": "sola scriptura"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the practice reenacting the last supper that split Protestantism?",
          "answer": "communion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Swiss theologian denied the Real Presence in communion?",
          "answer": "Ulrich Zwingli"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the German theologian who recorded and edited the Augsburg Confession?",
          "answer": "Philip Melanchthon"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "GERMAN UNIFICATION",
      "prompt": "During the process of German unification, who or what was…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The first German chancellor who engineered unification?",
          "answer": "Otto von Bismarck"
        },
        {
          "question": "The militaristic north German state which led unification?",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Prussia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The nation led by Napoleon III that was defeated in 1871, leading to the proclamation of the Second Reich?",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "The territory formed from two border regions that was annexed by Germany from its western neighbor?",
          "answer": "Alsace-Lorraine"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Danish border region seized in a war by the two leading powers of the German Confederation?",
          "answer": "Schleswig-Holstein"
        },
        {
          "question": "The king who became the first German Emperor?",
          "answer": "Wilhelm I"
        },
        {
          "question": "The royal house of the new German Emperors?",
          "answer": "Hohenzollern"
        },
        {
          "question": "The 1866 battle that ended Austrian hegemony over the German states?",
          "answer": "Battle of Sadowa"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CONSTITUTIONAL CONVENTION",
      "prompt": "During the Constitutional Convention, who or what…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City hosted the meeting in Independence Hall?",
          "answer": "Philadelphia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Presided over the meeting after leaving retirement at Mount Vernon?",
          "answer": "George Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Pennsylvanian who came to the meetings in a sedan chair?",
          "answer": "Benjamin Franklin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is known as the Father of the Constitution and took notes of the debates?",
          "answer": "James Madison"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proposal favoring the large states became the blueprint for the Constitution?",
          "answer": "Virginia Plan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor of Virginia from a famous family who did not sign the Constitution?",
          "answer": "Edmund Jennings Randolph"
        },
        {
          "question": "Competing plan that protected the rights of small states?",
          "answer": "New Jersey Plan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proposed the Connecticut Compromise, creating the House and Senate?",
          "answer": "Roger Sherman"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one of this artist’s paintings, the title officer is supported by several soldiers under a waving Union Jack during Battle of Jersey. George Augustus Eliott points toward several sinking Spanish soldiers in The Siege of (20 pts)",
        "Gibraltar, a work by this artist of The Death of Major Peirson. Another of his painting shows a silver kettle in the hands of the (10 pts)",
        "silversmith Paul Revere. In his most famous painting, El Morro castle looms behind a harpooner saving a man from an anatomically incorrect marine creature. For 10 points, name this painter of Watson and the Shark."
      ],
      "answer": "John Singleton Copley"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Duchy of Savoy was assured independence after this King’s forces won at the Battle of St. Quentin. His signing of the Treaty of Joinville prompted another ruler to sign the Treaty of Nonsuch. A revolt against the forces of this ruler sparked the (20 pts)",
        "Eighty Years’ War. This man’s brother John of Austria won the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Lepanto during his reign. The Battle of Gravelines prevented this man’s fleet from rendezvousing with the Duke of Parma and invading England. For 10 points, name this son of Charles V, the king of Spain who sent the Spanish Armada."
      ],
      "answer": "Philip II of Spain"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of the first times this group flexed its political muscle was when it torpedoed A.T. Stewart’s nomination as Treasury Secretary. Prominent opponents of this faction included Carl Schurz and William Robertson. This group, which was led by Thomas Platt and Roscoe (20 pts)",
        "Conkling, was detested by the Half-Breeds and Mugwumps, and Charles Guiteau proclaimed membership in this faction after shooting (10 pts)",
        "James Garfield. For 10 points, name this this group of pro-spoils system Republicans based in New York."
      ],
      "answer": "Stalwarts"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Traditionally, this empire was founded in 802 AD after one of its rulers completed a ceremony celebrating freedom from Javanese control. One ruler of this kingdom conquered parts of the (20 pts)",
        "Malay Peninsula, but lost wars to the neighboring states of Champa and Dai Viet. That ruler, Suryavarman II, portrayed himself as Vishnu in a (10 pts)",
        "monumental temple complex that was completed after his death. For 10 points, name this empire that built Angkor Wat and lent its name to a 20th century Communist group in Cambodia."
      ],
      "answer": "Khmer Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Nineteenth-century conflict in this country centered on the Bay of Plenty, which was the home of an indigenous guerrilla leader named Te Kooti. Dusky Sound is an inlet of this country's southwest coast, which was a major early center of jade production. The (20 pts)",
        "Otago gold rush took place in this country, whose indigenous people call it by a name that means “land of the long white cloud.” The Treaty of (10 pts)",
        "Waitangi was a controversial land document in, for 10 points, what island country in the southwest Pacific whose capital is Wellington?"
      ],
      "answer": "New Zealand"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2007, this country's military dictator suspended the chief justice of its supreme court and declared a state of emergency before resigning the next year. This country's president Pervez (20 pts)",
        "Musharraf seized power in a coup in 1999 soon after the indecisive (+) Kargil War. In this country's most recent elections, cricketer Imran Khan's political party finished in second place. In this country's city of (10 pts)",
        "Rawalpindi, opposition leader Benazir Bhutto was assassinated in 2007. For 10 points, name this country where Osama bin Laden was killed."
      ],
      "answer": "Islamic Republic of Pakistan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man commissioned a thousand-page white paper intended to prove that the U.S. had no hope of successful military intervention in China, which was perceived as an attempt to deflect criticism for “losing China” to the Communists during his time as (20 pts)",
        "Secretary. This man was accused of running a \"cowardly college of Communist (10 pts)",
        "containment\" by Richard Nixon and of overseeing a spy-riddled State Department by Joseph McCarthy. For 10 points, name this much-maligned Secretary of State who served under the second Truman administration until 1953."
      ],
      "answer": "Dean Gooderham Acheson"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The head of the losing commander at this battle was sent to Maroboduus, the king of the Marcomanni. Segestes, the begrudging father-in-law of this battle’s victor, tried to warn the losing commander prior to this battle, which mostly took place at (20 pts)",
        "Kalkriese Hill. At the subsequent Battle of the Weser River, Germanicus recovered a standard lost at this battle. After this battle, Augustus reportedly shouted (10 pts)",
        "“Varus, give me back my legions!” For 10 points, identify this 9 AD battle in which Arminius’ Germanic forces successfully ambushed three Roman legions."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Teutoburg Forest"
    }
  ]
}